Guide to the DePelchin Children's Center records, 1887-2000 MS 656
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
DePelchin Children's Center Records
1887-2000
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
DePelchin Children's Center
MS 656
7.0 Linear Feet 18 boxes
The materials in the DePelchin Children's Center records include the written and visual record of the Center ranging from 1887 to 2000. Highlights include correspondence from and photographs of the founder, Kezia Payne DePelchin. The collection does not contain records of adoptions.
Historical Note
DePelchin Children's Center, founded in 1892 in Houston, TX by Kezia Payne DePelchin as DePelchin Faith Home, was chartered on March 24, 1893. The home began with three young boys in the home of Agnes Perry at 2500 Washington Ave. It moved to the corner of Chenevert & Pierce Streets in 1899 to accommodate a growing number of children, followed in 1913 to 2700 Albany Street @ Tuam. The institute's charter was renewed in 1928 with a name change to DePelchin Faith Home and Children's Bureau to extend to the general care of children including foster home service, adoption, and child protective services. The name was changed again to DePelchin Children's Center in 1983 to include counseling, post-adoption services, maternity care, parent-preparation, and special education. The center outgrew its Albany Street location in 1938 and relocated to Shepherd & Memorial Drive, with new facilities at the same location in 2002.
Biographical Note
Kezia Payne DePelchin, founder of the institution, was born on July 23, 1828 to Catherine and Abraham Payne in the Madeira Islands of Portugal. Her mother died in 1833 and her father moved the family to America in 1836, with Galveston, Texas as the destination in 1837. A yellow fever outbreak saw several sisters return to Madeira, but several siblings and her father did not survive. Kezia and her governess moved to Houston in 1841 where Kezia taught music in Houston's first public schools. She married Adolf DePelchin in 1862, but within a year they separated and never divorced. Kezia acquired immunity to yellow fever and nursed its victims in Houston and then in Memphis, TN and Senatobia, MS between 1878 and 1879. She returned to Houston and became the first matron of Bayland Orphan's Home for Boys between ages 6 and 12. In 1892 she was approached with three orphan boys too young to be accepted by Bayland, and asked friend Agnes Perry to supply a room for the boys' care. The DePelchin Faith Home was established, but Kezia died soon after on Jan. 13, 1893.
Scope and Contents
The materials in the DePelchin Children's Center records include the written and visual record of the Center ranging from 1887 to 2000. Highlights include correspondence from and photographs of the founder, Kezia Payne DePelchin. The collection does not contain records of adoptions.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research with restrictions as noted. The collection does not contain records of adoptions. Requests for adoption applictions should be forwarded to DePelchin Children's Center administration.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were gifted by the DePelchin Children's Center on June 14, 2016, with addendum on April 11, 2018.
Related Materials
See also Kezia Payne DePelchin diary, 1878-1879, MS201; "From Houston to Memphis: the Kezia Payne DePelchin Letters and the Yellow Fever Epidemic of 1878" by Adrian S. Melissinos; "Candle by Night: the Story of the Life and Times of Kezia Payne DePelchin" by Harold Jackson Matthews.
Index Terms
Subjects
Social life and customs; African Americans; Orphans; Children; Women
Document Types
photographs; letters (correspondence); scrapbooks
Subjects (Corporations)
DePelchin Children's Center
- Series I: Administrative
  - By-laws, 1925, 1937, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation, Negro Child Center, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Licenses: State Board of Control, State Department of Public Welfare, 1933, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Proclamations: City of Houston, [U.S.] Presidential, 1968, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Baker Botts Baker & Lovett, James A. Baker, Jr., 1893-03-25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bright, Stewart, 1961-01-24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Carter, Rosalynn, 2000-05-08 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Crittendon Services, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Darst, Sheila Stewart, 1984-04-25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - DePelchin, Kezia, 1850-1851 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - DePelchin, Kezia, 1875-07 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - DePelchin, Kezia, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - DePelchin, Kezia, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - DePelchin, Kezia, 1887-1891 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - DePelchin, Kezia, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Directives, 1894, 1906, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Endt, T.B. to T.W. House, 1894-04-08 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Greeting cards, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Kilgore, Mrs. M.E., 1896, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lee, Marie, 1918-09-30 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Negro Child Center, 1951-11-19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Payne, Martha, 1893, 1895, 1907, 1916, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Teague, James U., 1973-02-06 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Wilson, Harvey T.D., 1907-03-26 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Donations
    - Various, 1893-1897 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Various, 1913, 1922, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Various, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Drawing, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Invitations, 1988-02-09 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Facilities
    - DePelchin Children's Center, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Negro Child Center (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Morrow residence, 3000 Calumet Dr., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Presentations
    - DePelchin Faith Home, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Child Welfare League, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Crittenton Services, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - San Jacinto Museum of History (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Reports
  - Crittenton Services historical (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Crittenton Services, 1929-1939, 1969, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - DePelchin Faith Home
    - 1917 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1922 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1929 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1946 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Boatwright family, 1925-1929 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Board of Director meeting minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Study and proposal of current emergency services, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Reaccreditation study, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Forms (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Kezia DePelchin historical (see also 4.6 for marriage record) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Residents, 1895, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Negro Child Center Governing Board meeting minutes, 1949-1954 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series III: Publicity
  - Advertisements, 1967, 1971, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Child Guidance Center, 1959, 1982 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Crittenton Services, 1962, 1968, 1971, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "The Informer" articles for Crittenton Services, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - DePelchin Faith Home
    - Newsclips, 1890s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Newsclips, 1910-1925 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Newsclips, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Newsclips, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Newsclips, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Newsclips, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Newsclips, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Newsclips, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Newsclips, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Newsclips, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Newsclips, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Golden Cradle Adoption Agency, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Negro Child Center (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Phantom fathers, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Newsclips (oversize)
    - 1927-1930 (scrapbook) (Box 18)
    - 1932-1936 (scrapbook) (Box 18)
    - 1934-1937 (scrapbook) (Box 18)
    - 1935-1938 (scrapbook) (Box 18)
    - 1957-1962 (scrapbook) (Box 18)
    - Loose, various (Box 18)
- Series IV: Publications
  - Annual Reports
    - 1923, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1925 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1926 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1927 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1929 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1930-1934 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1935 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1936 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1937, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1940, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1946 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 1981 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1983 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 1984 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 1984-85 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - 1985-86 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - 1986-87 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - 1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - 1990 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - 1991 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - 1992 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - 1993 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - 1994 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - 1995 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - 1996 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - 2002 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 2009 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 2010 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 2011 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 2012 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 2013 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 2014 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 2015 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Today"
    - 1987 Fall (Box 16)
    - 1990 Summer (Box 16)
    - 1991 Spring (Box 16)
    - 1992 Fall (Box 16)
    - 1993 Spring (Box 16)
    - 1993 Summer (Box 16)
    - 1994 June (Box 16)
    - 1994 Fall (Box 16)
    - 1994 Winter (Box 16)
    - 1995 Summer (Box 16)
    - 1995 Winter (Box 16)
    - 1996 Spring (Box 16)
    - 1997 Winter (Box 16)
    - 1998 Spring (Box 16)
    - 1998 Summer (Box 16)
    - 1998 Fall (Box 16)
    - 1998 Winter (Box 16)
    - 1999 Spring (Box 16)
    - 1999 Summer (Box 16)
    - 1999 Fall (Box 16)
    - 1999 Winter (Box 16)
    - 2000 Spring (Box 16)
    - 2000 Summer (Box 16)
    - 2000 Fall (Box 16)
    - 2001 Spring (Box 16)
    - 2001 Summer (Box 16)
    - 2001 Fall (Box 16)
    - 2001 Winter (Box 16)
    - 2002 Summer (Box 16)
    - 2002 Fall (Box 16)
    - 2002 Winter (Box 16)
    - 2003 Spring (Box 16)
    - 2003 Fall/Winter (Box 16)
    - 2003 Winter (Box 16)
    - 2004 Spring (Box 16)
    - 2004 Summer (Box 16)
    - 2004 Fall (Box 16)
    - 2004 Winter (Box 16)
    - 2005 Spring (Box 16)
    - 2005 Summer (Box 16)
    - 2005 Fall (Box 16)
    - 2005 Winter (Box 16)
    - 2006 Spring (Box 16)
    - 2006 Summer (Box 16)
    - 2006 Fall (Box 16)
    - 2006 Winter (Box 16)
    - 2007 Spring (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 2009 Summer (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "An Introduction to the DePelchin Faith Home and Children's Bureau, Houston, Texas", 1949 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Listing of Community Services: Definitions, Estimates of Volume, Estimates of Needs", 1961-07 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cullen Bayou Place (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - DePelchin Children's Center prospectus, ca. 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - DePelchin Children's Center adoption brochures (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - DePelchin Children's Center "Today" fact sheets, 1985-86, 1987-88 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "DePelchin Faith Home News", 1930-11-15 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - DePelchin Faith Home Chrysantheum Show flyers/brochures, 1902, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Family Friends of DePelchin; Executive Committee Orientation Booklet", 1997/98 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Crittenton Services (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Crittenton Services brochures (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "The Ima Hogg Foundation", ca. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "The Trained Nurse and Hospital Review", 1933-12 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Houston and Harris County (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Abstract of Title: Block 1& 3 Cushing Park (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Series V: Realia
  - Crittenton Services stationery samples (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - The Park People, Harris County Tree Registry certificate and book for DePelchin Children's Center "The Therapy Tree", 2000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Marriage record of Adolphe DePelchin and Keziah Payne (photostat), 1862-08-23 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Guest book, 10-30-1978, 10-17-1979, 12-16-1982, 3-30-1992 (Box 8)
  - Book of Remembrance of the Negro Child Center (Box 8)
  - The Building Fund of the Negro Child Center--donors guest book (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Negro Child Center (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Cloth pages, 1880s-1890s (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Loose pages--Mary Adelaid Hynes [?] (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Cloth pages in cash book, 1886-1903 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Florence Crittendon Home, 1928-1955 (Box 17)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Babies [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Boys-individuals (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Boys-two or more [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Girls-individuals [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Girls-two or more [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Teens [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Children-two or more & groups [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - Children-groups [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Adults [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Mrs. T.W. House (Box 17)
  - Adults with babies (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Adults with boys (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Adults with girls (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Adults with children [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - Foster parents [see also oversize Box 17] (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Kezia DePelchin, family, residences (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Staff (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Board members (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Committee chairs & members (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Program speakers & performers (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Jackson Hicks-caterer (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Events
    - Ben Johnson rodeo (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Rodeo (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Hoe Down (Houston Oilers) (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Circus (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Halloween (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Thanksgiving, 1930s (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Christmas, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Theatrical (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Photon family day, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Negro Child Center (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified (Box 12, Folder 17-19)
    - Unidentified (Box 13, Folder 1-7)
  - Facilities
    - Aerials (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Construction (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Dedication, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Groundbreaking-Negro Children's Center [?] (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Groundbreaking, 1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Groundbreaking-Cullen Bayou Place (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Exteriors, Albany St. (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Exterior, Chenevert & Pierce Sts. (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Exteriors, Looscan St. (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Exteriors, Scotland St. (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Exteriors (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Interiors (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Crittenton Services (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Florence Crittenton Rescue Car (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Davenport facility (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Faith Home Farm, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Houston Child Guidance Center (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Pine Tree Camp, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Signs (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - News conference, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Newsletter (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Early unknown (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Portraits (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Negatives & proof sheets (Box 15, Folder 1-5)
  - Oversize (Box 17)
  - Oversize (Box 18)